truthfully I went from knowing this much
about saa's effects on our
cardiovascular health to this much and
yet that small transformation is packed
with information that I'll share with
you now I probably don't need to explain
sauna to you but it's a room where you
experience a dry or wet heat session and
the health claims abound related to it
but are they accurate and if we crack
open some studies on the topic here's
what the research says on its
Effectiveness in this analysis
researchers pulled together all the
intervention studies using sauna as
their primary intervention they also
focused on people who already had
pre-existing cardiovascular disease and
focused on including studies that lasted
a few weeks at minimum now unfortunately
they did not pre-register this analysis
nor did they include a database that
contains failed studies that weren't
published which is unfortunate still
looking at the data there's some cause
for happy pause so I'm going to walk you
through some pretty regular measures of
heart disease that you've heard of
before and then we're going to get into
one that requires a bit more physiology
background and I'll explain that one as
well of course if we pop open the data
on blood pressure here we're looking at
a limited Force plots on the overall raw
changes in blood pressure from sauna use
both graphs represent blood pressure the
left one is systolic blood pressure so
the top number when you get your blood
pressure check and the right graph is
the diastolic blood pressure so the
lower number on your test the studies
are listed on the left side of each and
we can see the neutral line above zero
this line indicates there's no
improvement with SAA use the squares and
lines indicate the study results and if
they move to the left they indicate that
there's a reduction in blood pressure
you can focus on the overall effects
Diamond which encompasses all of the
data there at the bottom so based on
both sauna seems to improve blood
pressure by a moderate amount so about a
5.5 unit drop in syy all again about a
6.5 unit drop in diastolic if you're
wondering what the 0 minutes and 30
minutes there stand for that's the
amount of time before the person keeled
over some people it was instant and
other people it took about 30 minutes if
you think that I'm being serious now
you've been
bamboozled they actually correspond to
if measurements were done immediately or
after 30 minutes outside of the sauna in
a towel resting the data is a little
more all over the place when we look at
the diastolic blood pressure front but
with limited studies there still seems
to be an effect
regardless I'd also note that Saun a
reliably elevated heart rate but only
when measured immediately not 30 minutes
later as seen here and that makes sense
you've had 30 minutes of cooling off
your body will return to its normal
state which is why the Black Diamond
overlaps the zero line the generalized
idea behind the benefits of increasing
heart rate is that sauna acts as a bit
of an exercise especially endurance
exercise mimetic to be clear this
doesn't mean that waiting 30 minutes
makes sauna ineffective it merely is a
difference in the measurement time and
nothing to say about sauna
Effectiveness okay now let's bring you
into your heart I'll ignore the cobwebs
and let's focus on a measure a concept
called left ventricular ejection
fraction here's where I get to tap into
my exercise physiology degree your heart
has a section called The ventricle and
The ventricle is responsible for the
musling blood out of this bottom section
through the aorta and into the rest of
your cardiovascular system normally your
left ventricle is excellent at this
objective and does it many times per
minute to keep you alive however if the
muscle is weakened or the pressure in
the aorta is too high or some other
hindrance the blood is not fully pushed
out of The ventricle during the heart
contraction and more of it is left in
the ventricle chamber this is measured
through ejection fraction there's more
to it than that but just know that the
lower your ejection fraction the worse
your heart condition typically because
less blood is being kicked out of the
heart so your heart is less effective so
that's not good okay so does sauna help
fascinatingly yeah it seems it does this
follows the same ideas as last time but
it's grouped by length of the study
ultimately everything considered at the
very bottom we see that the ventricular
ejection fraction increases by about
three points of course this isn't Earth
shattering but it's no doubt an
improvement by the way there's a few
different sauna protocols used in these
studies with some being more popular
than others and there's some info on
duration and frequency that I'll be
covering in the extended version of this
video which is part of the physionic
Insiders it also comes with monthly
podcasts weekly articles a full video
library a private community and much
more so check it out it's linked in the
description box now if you're a
cardiologist which if you are hello uh
you might be wondering why they chose
ejection fraction as a measure and if
you're not a cardiologist you're
wondering why this even matters well it
turns out that while the study is framed
like it's about cardiovascular fitness
over 90% of the studies included in this
analysis were in heart failure patients
where ejection fraction matters a lot
more than the average person
unfortunately extending that out even
until other cardiovascular diseases
which have a different ideology is
difficult to do so I think think it
would be best to limit the ejection
fraction data to people with some level
of heart failure however the blood
pressure and heart rate changes are
likely applicable across the board as
further evidenced in this scientific
review so they actually mention several
other benefits like reductions in
inflammation reduce blood fats reduce
oxidative stress and several other
clinical metrics everything considered
there are some flaws in this analysis
but that doesn't detract from the
overall point here that can be plainly
stated as sauna reduces the risk of
cardiovascular disease even extending to
improving heart failure modestly if you
have access to one it's probably an easy
addition to your life with a pretty good
payoff healthwise and if you care about
your heart health I'd certainly consider
this easy change too while you're at it
I'll catch you over there don't run too
fast though